[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, today's sutta is Samyutta Agama 616 and that is the Chinese parallel to the famous simile of the cook.
[SPEAKER_00]: This one is kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, maybe just because I'm used to that Pali sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: This one seems more descriptive or something, I don't know, but maybe it's just a novelty, because it's written differently or something, but I still find it quite useful, so that's why I thought we can go through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, thus have I heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: At one time, the Buddha was staying in Jeta Grove, Anathapindika's Park, in the country of Sravasti.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that time, the World Honored One said to the bhikkhus,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you should take the sign of your own citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do not let it scatter outward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if a bhikkhu is foolish, undiscerning and unskillful, not taking the sign of his own citta, but taking external signs instead, then afterward, he declines and gives rise to obstruction in himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a cook who is foolish, undiscerning and not skillful in the expedient means, mixing together the various flavors in service and of nourishment for his lord.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sour, salty, pungent, bland.
[SPEAKER_00]: These do not accord with his lord's wishes, but he's unable
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what does that remind you of?
[SPEAKER_00]: If this doesn't accord with his lord's wishes, the lord is displeased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being displeased, he grants him neither rank nor reward, nor does he hold affection for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of guesswork, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just has his ideas, his preferences, that then he just kind of hopes would work out for the king.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a hit and miss.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even when it's a hit, he doesn't know why it is a hit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it's a miss, he doesn't know why it's a miss.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, he's just locked in his own projections.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the foolish bhikkhu is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, undiscerning and unskillful dwelling in the contemplation of the body within the body, he's unable to remove and cut off the higher afflictions, unable to gather and take hold of his own citta,
[SPEAKER_00]: Likewise, unable to attain inward quietude of citta, unable to attain supreme right mindfulness, right clear knowing, likewise unable to attain the four kinds of higher citta states, the pleasant abiding and the secure nirvana not previously attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he cannot
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is called a bhikkhu who is foolish, undiscerning, unskillful, unable to skillfully gather the inner sign of citta while taking on external signs, thereby giving rise to obstructions in himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... we'll address, obviously, all these subtle points, but you can see the obstructions do not arise because you perceive things by sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: The obstructions arise because you are unable to skillfully gather the citta internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you are unable to maintain the context, contain the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, these things obstruct you.
[SPEAKER_00]: In and of themselves, they're not obstructions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obstructions come from undeveloped citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on the other hand, if there is a bhikkhu who is wise, intelligent, eloquent, skillful in expedient means, having first taken the inner sign of citta, afterward taking external signs, then at the later time he never declines, nor gives rise to obstruction himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a cook who is wise, intelligent, eloquent, and skillful in expedient means, serving and nourishing his lord, able to harmonize the various flavors, while grasping the sign of what his lord delights in, harmonizing the various flavors in accordance with his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Listening to the flavors his lord desires, he repeatedly serves them up, and once the lord is pleased, he will certainly receive rank, emolument, and affection bestowed upon him grows even greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he'll be rewarded for his efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same goes for the bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, correctly dwelling in contemplation of the body within the body, he cuts off the higher afflictions, skillfully gathers his citta, inwardly steals the citta, possesses right mindfulness, clear knowing, attains the four higher citta states, the pleasant abiding in this very life, attains the secure nirvana previously unattained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is called a bhikkhu who is eloquent, skillful in expedient means, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes the same for the contemplation of feeling, mind and phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the four satipaṭṭhānas, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the bhikkhus rejoiced in the Buddha's words.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the main, like, the main point, really, main point from the sutta is just like the core, like in the Pali, is
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the signs of your own citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: We spoke about it many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: The suttas mention it as a prerequisite to sotāpārthi, which also has its own prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the sign of the mind was conditioned upon dwelling in seclusion, but not just some like a mechanical physical isolation,
[SPEAKER_00]: But the actual, true viveka, internal viveka, internal seclusion, which is seclusion from lust, lustful intentions, let alone lustful acts, aversion, intentions of ill will, let alone, you know, acts of anger and so on, and even the delusion, obviously, the distraction and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, internally,
[SPEAKER_00]: means you would have had to be secluded from those things sufficiently enough, even if you're not necessarily able to abide in the physical seclusion, though, of course, physical seclusion help, can help, and always helps these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those are the prerequisites for seeing the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, cittanimitta, as often heard and read about, can also become a thing that's sort of mystified as well, because people try to wrap their head around it, you know, what's cittanimitta, how to see my signs of the mind, which is a prerequisite for sotāpati and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then it's kind of, you know, gets equated with meditation experiences, visions and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's really not what the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither this āgama parallel, nor the actual Pali.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really just something that you can see, if you know where to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like hidden behind a veil of ignorance, that you just need to, through some, you know, magical absorption, kind of, wake up to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically, if the mind is obstructed, as the Sutta says, it's because of your doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you're foolish, you're incompetent, you don't know what to pay attention to, you're ignoring what... how King reacts and what he does, and just serve your own preferences on top of it, and are absolutely convinced and locked in those ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you don't see your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like the first question,
[SPEAKER_00]: that I posted was pretty much like... how to see?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, do I see signs of my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can ask yourself that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the answer is no, why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, there is no an external condition that's preventing you from seeing the internal signs of your citta, as the sutra says.
[SPEAKER_00]: External signs, external conditions remain unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they play no part in you not seeing the signs of the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there has to be a reason for obstruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't be, oh, I'm doing everything right, but I'm not still seeing the signs of my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're doing everything right, there would be no obstructions that are obstructing your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would be seeing the signs of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The indications, the characteristics, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ask yourself, do I see the signs of my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the answer is no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, again, let that question sink in.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is now stopping me from seeing the internal characteristics of my own wild animal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is the... what is the convergence point?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a, say, like you could say, you know, seclusion necessary, withdrawal from unwholesome states, withdrawal from sensuality, withdrawal from ill-will, withdrawal from distraction, withdrawal from hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do all these things have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: In a sense, what do... What is the main carrier, let's put it that way, of all those things, of all these obstructive states?
[SPEAKER_00]: What defines obstruction as obstruction and non-obstruction as non-obstruction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much, what is a single factor because of which you're not seeing the signs of your mind yet?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the answer is... it's your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's cetanā.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, even linguistically speaking, citta and cetanā carries that connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Citta as a sort of a, say, you could say, accumulated horizon, and cetanā would be the expression of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: You start by your own intentions being driven, by ignorance, by hindrances, by aversion, by greed, by lust, by acts out, by body, by speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you come across the dhamma, you learn it rightly, you start to actually train in virtue and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like all of that, the sole purpose of that, is to, well, first reduce, then contain and prevent the expressions of corrupted citta, of the wild animal, as I often compare it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that in and of itself, like abstaining from certain behaviors, as necessary as it is, in and of itself, will not necessarily
[SPEAKER_00]: be able to address the mental aspect of those intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what's missing for people that, say, are keeping the precepts of training rightly, but still not being sotāpānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because on the level of these, like, mental layers, the unwholesome intentions are still not sufficiently seen, sufficiently restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are still entertained and accepted.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you don't say anything bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you don't do anything by the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mentally, when those intentions present themselves, you do take them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do accept them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do allow them to occupy you, to proliferate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the single factor for somebody not being a sotāpanna is not having fully, sufficiently contained, endured rightly and eventually uprooted or seen beyond the roots of the unwholesome intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And consequently, that's how you would do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to
[SPEAKER_00]: See the signs of the mind, so that you can, you know, understand the nature of dukkha and Four Noble Truths and be a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the entire training, everything that you've been doing so far and you're planning to do, pretty much needs to be leading up to the point of recognizing the unwholesome intentions, even on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's the whole, you know, so many talks, in so many other talks that I often talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you know, like you can, as I said, precepts are necessary, virtue is necessary, sense restraint is necessary, but you can adhere to it, you can take it on and kind of get used to it and really never break the precepts for a hundred years.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at the same time, never allow those same principles of precepts and sense restraint to come too close on those mental levels.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a bit much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you tolerate it there, you allow it there, you engage with it there, but you never let it go too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's not good enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your goal is right view, that's not good enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the measure of suitable intentions, skillful intentions, or unskillful that obstruct, and skillful that don't obstruct,
[SPEAKER_00]: is by your own presently enduring intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not by your views or ideas or how you think things should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's kind of that second part where it says the foolish cook has his own ideas what to do, but he has no reference point
[SPEAKER_00]: And most people's Buddhist practice is that today.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, mechanical techniques, absorption methods, I don't know, squint three feet in front of your eye for three minutes before you... like these random things, random observances, random exercises, body scanning and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that relate to the actual, you know, citta, the king, in terms of which direction is it sending the animal?
[SPEAKER_00]: What message is it conveying?
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't even see the king.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, king's mind, king's preferences do not exist for a foolish person.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's been told he has to serve the meal and he serves it according to his own concocted ideas, theory, you know, tradition, authority, whatever he chose to use to justify.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that results in he himself not seeing his own intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why he's never gonna see the king and never be able to actually address it right and recognize, oh, hold on, when I attend to these things, when I intend them, act out, this is the result of my citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by the way, it doesn't matter why.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could say, well, the whole, the entire world does this thing and it's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that might be objectively true.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not true for you in terms of your practice and where the values should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, for whatever reason, when I do that thing that the whole world does, my mind gets enraged, or my mind gets infected with lust, or my mind gets distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I can say, yeah, but, you know, that's secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really, it's not a problem, because if it's a problem, the world wouldn't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the wrong reference.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that projected idea of a foolish man who thinks, I'll be doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't really matter what my own mind, what the king is hinting at.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where you need to... the beginning of, like, like, discernment of that reference point of your own wild animal, of your own citta, is... you gotta start, first and foremost, recognizing the pretty much the broader sense that contains... of your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole world is doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but why am I doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the... that's the question you always need to have at the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much as an enduring context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever you're doing, you're looking as to, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, initially, as I said, maybe for somebody new to this, it can be a bit kind of, oh, I'm doing this because of this or because of that, and you fall into this psychological kind of patterns and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You calm down, but the context will remain of whatever's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the same time, you're looking as to, what's my reason for doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, not to arrive at some great revelation, or I'm doing it because of this, or justification for that matter, but to see whether it's rooted in lust, aversion, distraction, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: delusion, or other hindrances, if you want to approach it through a hindrance side.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's your reference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you would become truly experienced, the true viveka, from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by going on top of a mountain, which, as I said, can help, but in and of itself, it's not going to do the work for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only way to truly seclude yourself, as a prerequisite to see the signs of your mind, the only way to truly seclude yourself from unwholesome states, is through discerning your intentions and not fueling the unwholesome ones, the obstructive ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do that long enough, you'll be secluded from all the obstruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're secluded from all the obstructions, the prerequisite for seeing the signs of the mind, dwelling in seclusion, will be met.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start seeing your own mind as an independent living entity, pretty much in the heart of your being, not a theoretical projection, not a mystical belief or some, you know, magical hope.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual living thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like mind within the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like now, whenever you think my mind is just my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you discern that your own mind, whatever idea of my mind I have as my mind, has its own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I have no access to that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't decide for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just meet it, meet it, whichever way basically has changed or a reason for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly what Satipaṭṭhāna Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows mind of lust as mind of lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not he changes mind of lust into something more suitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: By knowing it for what it is, you see where the line of your effort and your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not knowing what it is, where it is, to what extent it is, by not seeing that king actually has preferences to what you're doing, you just be stabbing in the dark, as most people do, and just do this and do that, guided by your own preference of what feels good for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for the king.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for the mind within the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're secluded enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll see the signs of that mind within the mind, an independent mind of your mind, sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see that, you do have a prerequisite for understanding the nature of dukkha, because that's the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the root of craving, which is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is the root of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind that you're not seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, pretty much, somebody who is seeing their mind on account of sufficiently maintaining, protecting the context of beneficial intentions and not fueling the unbeneficial ones, regardless of what the world, authority, tradition, peers, whoever says, your intention
[SPEAKER_00]: The roots of your intention are the criteria for whether you will be tolerating it mentally, acting out of it physically or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's also not incidental, why nobody can just choose to do that kind of spontaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'll just spontaneously ignore the pressure of the senses, the pressure of the world, the pressure of the authority, the pressure of the history, of the tradition, and just stay on this level of like, yeah, but my intention is rooted in lust, therefore I won't follow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you really need to have a good reason to stick there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, again, the learning and the right instruction is obviously very important.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't start rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you can have all the instruction you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have the Buddha himself reciting dhamma for you 50 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, again, you are not looking at the intentions behind your actions, behind your speech, behind your thoughts, you're not going to do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do I see the signs of my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Unwholesome as in obstructive.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might not be...
[SPEAKER_00]: These intentions might not be overtly, kind of coarsely, bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, deep down, you know, whenever you're about to do something, say something, you know where it is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's, you know, subtle desire, subtle restlessness, subtle this, subtle that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that needs to be seen sufficiently enough and recognized and familiarized with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is pretty much the gateway to discerning the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: That then needs taming and training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that was kind of the second question that came on the base of this sutta was like the foolish cook serves according to his own ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same, as I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, you know, I like to sit and do the body scanning every night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: For you specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever practice you're doing, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see any connection?
[SPEAKER_00]: To the citta, to the training, do you see how it how it translates, how it relates, how it conveys the messages?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there such a such a kind of like a like a field that's that's that's connected to that, you know, the the citta and the inner signs of training?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't really know, because I'm told to, because I've been trying and I found it helpful,
[SPEAKER_00]: Helpful in what way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pacifying you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Removing the disturbances?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, many things can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that make them unobstructive, in terms of seeing the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what's the criteria that you follow when you practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what's the criteria that the foolish cook... By the way, you're a foolish cook, if you're not seeing your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody starts as a foolish cook.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, I did something wrong and I became a foolish cook.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody starts as a foolish cook.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't change that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, instead of ignoring it, yeah, you accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the Sutta clearly says, if I'm not seeing my own mind, it's because I am maintaining the obstructions of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am foolish in that regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean like, oh, I'm an idiot, worthless person or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are two coarse things.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is like on the level of
[SPEAKER_00]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I seeing my intentions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I using the criteria of those intentions for whether I should follow inclinations to say something, do something, think something, or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I just ignoring that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everybody starts as a foolish cook, but nobody needs to stay a foolish cook, and people won't stay a foolish cook if they make the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever practice you're doing, you need to know why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there is no external justification, external signs that can justify ignoring the internal context, the internal counterpart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing can come in place of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever practice you're doing, sit down and ask yourself, why am I doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the benefit?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, whatever answer comes up, question that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same, even if, say, if you're not doing the mindless techniques or body scanning and stuff like that, that I always criticize, say, yeah, I'm keeping the precepts and reading the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you are actually doing those things, when you're making the effort to sustain those things, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason why you need to ask those questions, because
[SPEAKER_00]: There's gonna be like a... already a lot of implicit expectations that will remain uncovered.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, I'm listening to Ajahn Amolie and, you know, I'm not doing, as I said, mindless techniques or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm keeping the precepts and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because deep down, I expect something will happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something right will happen because I found the best teacher now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, as I said, you can find the Buddha himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't result in what you're hoping to result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're maintaining that gap between things actually done, in terms of practice, by body, speech and mind, such as not cultivating, as I said, the bad bodily behavior, verbal behavior, but then training in the same principles of the mental behavior,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person wouldn't go as far and then would adopt the practice through the external signs, through the talks and suttas and stuff, but leave that internal gap where the intentions are, filled with hope and expectation that these external things I'm doing will bring up citta, nimitta and sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is not as wrong as say somebody completely mindlessly just doing mechanical body scanning without a grain of thought or self-reflection, but it's still on the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still not gonna result in the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the intentions, your own intentions, your own cetanā, which is always manifested from that citta, which is a horizon for it, so to speak, remains completely ignored.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like invisible or not seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just not valued enough to be used sufficiently as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, my intentions are hidden from me or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the most inauthentic person that just lives perpetually in a state of bad faith, consumed by sensuality, ill will, and just acting, reacting to impulses, even they
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot truly obscure their intention at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why deep down everybody knows what they're doing and why they're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might ignore it, they might keep the momentum going so that they never had to stop and look back at it, but that cannot be covered.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the nature of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are paired with the citta, you're paired with the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... you can be covering it up all you want, it's always going to be there right underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cetanas, your intentions, are not mysteriously hidden.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to do a new set of practice to reveal that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're there.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're engaged with.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're multiplied through your own reflection and chosen and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just not valued enough as something to stick to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have... it's not a big thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a big problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a thought, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm not gonna say anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not gonna do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, when it comes up, that choice...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always a choice, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the Nyanamoli Thera, the first, and Nyanavira used to translate it, if I remember correctly, in their early letters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they're talking about translating cetanā as choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's always on the level when you exercise choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you do exercise choice, which means there is always self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot exercise a choice when you are unaware.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can do a choice habitually, but there is still awareness of the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just ignoring it and not emphasizing it enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I've been talking about it in previous talks, like, recognizing that choice and sticking to the right one whenever there is enough self-awareness to know that, oh, that's that choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to be perfect from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to be, you know, ignoring, falling for it, distracted from it and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you learn enough, you'll be catching it more and more, the moments when you make this choice, choices,
[SPEAKER_00]: Before you make them and then not make them, that's the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice is not, oh, I'm aware of the moment now and I feel my body and the universe and experience as a whole or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice is not to make the wrong choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what's the wrong choice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, anything that obstructs.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it that obstructs?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it obstructs the mind if it's rooted in lust, desire, greed,
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion, ill will, irritation, distraction, mindlessness, laziness, spread it to the hindrances, in all sorts of synonyms and whatever works for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but, also, at the same time, if it's not rooted in that, you don't need to... you don't need... you can choose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, it can feel like, oh, I have to police everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just so confining, so restricting.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is because you don't know where the line for your responsibility and your actual doing is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, say, you know, you start doing it, you put up with it, it becomes more freeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you realize, okay, if it's not rooted in those things, I don't need to police it, I don't need to worry about it, I don't need to be catching moment to moment so my mindfulness doesn't slip and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if the doubt comes up, which you will initially recognize, okay, now I have a choice in regard to the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before, I wasn't aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before, whenever hindrance came up, it would pressure me and I would just get caught up in this cycle and I couldn't stop until I was just tired, basically, and forgot about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what comes up through that animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind of my mind, what brings up.
[SPEAKER_00]: My choice in regard to it remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't get closer, doesn't go further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remains at the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that door I keep talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't open the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what's trying to get in or trying to pressure you to open it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you recognize that, the more confident you become in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any state of mind, and that's again the satipaṭṭhāna done rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depressed mind has depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, I'm not accepting the choices that depressed mind is offering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Elated mind, distracted mind, any state of mind, elevated, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the recognition of the line of the choice and the cetan and intention remains unchanged and that's the gateway, that's my door to basically training the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have all the other advanced, the actual, you know, higher mind training.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the suttas described, which is, you know, those perceptions presented to that mind, contemplating this sufficiently enough, so that the mind stops resisting, stops trying to outrun, and stops reacting to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all that can be done once you actually see the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like... again, people can... people would be doing it in the same sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: A foolish cook gets all new ideas because he came across new recipe books, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: new suttas, and then he's just blindly doing this and that.
[SPEAKER_00]: One week this, another retreat that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No internal connection and recognition to how that affects the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, another aspect here, although I kind of covered all the questions pretty much, but anyway...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can go quickly through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can I recognize the difference between my experience of the external objects and, as in, you know, engaging with the senses and so on, and the underlying state of mind that is concurrently enduring in relation to them?
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words,
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I at least able to some extent to not be completely absorbed in what the senses offer, the sense objects, and maintain some notion of the context of the background in relation to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where your intentions are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're never going to see intentions in sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, because that's why you're looking at them, because of the intentions not seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intentions not seen are sending you in the directions of these sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the recollection of the body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, how do you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the body within the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the mind within the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we...
[SPEAKER_00]: I answered it, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you look at the body, any idea that you have of it, it's not the actual body.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a body within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body, they can only be seen indirectly on account of purifying all of your intentions in relation to that body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where are those intentions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even there and then, when you're asking yourself, there is intention to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ask yourself, okay, why am I asking myself this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing what Ajahn Mahārāj said to do now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I have faith or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it, the aspect that inspires faith in me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing should be taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because to the extent you take things for granted, to that extent you have obscured your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, again, it goes without saying, it's not going to be perfectly clean overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suddenly all intentions are pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's a training.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the effort that requires repetition and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you better start doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even things that, yeah, are self-evident.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's right and if I understand it as right, well, I'll be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why am I not a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't matter if you're a householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's not an excuse either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because no amount of household life, external science, as I said, can come in between you and your own intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your own doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your intentions are not pure enough, because of which you're not seeing the signs of the mind, because of which you're not understanding the Four Noble Truths that are not Sotāpanna, it's your own doing, on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your own choices are still
[SPEAKER_00]: Made in a way that's actually obstructing seeing the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, start making the right ones and even if you don't want to become a sotāpanna, you will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it needs to be done on that mental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, okay, I made the choice, keep the precepts and I'll just blindly stick to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mentally, when things come up, when the possibility to choose rightly and say no to such thoughts, say no to such proliferations, I tolerate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't make those... that effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I know I won't do it by the body or speech, so this is fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like again, the roots remain infected.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... so, yeah, like, when the Sutta talks about, you know, the inner sign and stuff, it's... it's... it's just what I mean by context.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I often say you develop the right context and then you sustain that context in regard to your engagement with the world, that's going to be inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sight, sounds, mouth, taste, touches, things having to do and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the context does not need to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the context starts to suffer, then you need to restrain yourself and pull yourself back until you can re-establish the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Context of, well, I will not lose the sight of my intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will certainly not give in to the, as I said, the wide basis of, like, carelessness, lust, and so on, because, again, it would fuel the mind in the wrong way, and then I would have a lot more to undo.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just in case, I don't know, for somebody maybe it's not clear, the intentions are not these momentary things that, oh, I just missed it now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Came, I made it to choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intention can last for five days, if the choice lasts for five days.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, you are abstaining from choice for five days.
[SPEAKER_00]: That same intention, same state of mind is there for five days.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you are aware of it, that's where it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why would you be even looking at the momentary movements and changes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Only because you don't know where the emphasis is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only because... again... See, the foolish cook
[SPEAKER_00]: You can kind of tell the king is not pleased, but still doesn't have a clue why, as to, like, what has he done right or wrong, or...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's just getting paranoid about everything he does now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everything becomes a problem, basically, because he doesn't know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let me now just monitor everything, but you're still monitoring it at a completely wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem was never in things that you can perceive through your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem was always in the intentions, your own choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have an intention for five days because you're abstaining from the choice, but the mind keeps bringing it back.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you bear that sense of confinement?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nagging, weighing down, increasing in weight?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even saying, yeah, it's weird, like, I shouldn't be thinking about it for five days.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just a small thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just a small thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a hassle to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, let me just act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me just psychologize it until I find a pleasing solution mentally, or let me go and say something if it was concerning others, or let me do something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you made a wrong choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you chose to give in
[SPEAKER_00]: To the pressure of the animal, to the pressure of the untrained mind, and did a random thing as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the choice lasts five days, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still don't make... well, you do the right abstaining from the wrong choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the choice then lasts for three months, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But three months have to keep this ambiguity, this...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it will all go away, literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: This mental problem and the pressure would go away if I just go and talk to that person.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it would go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what would also go away is your own mind with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you would obstruct it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for you, doesn't matter if it's not a problem for that person, doesn't matter if it's not a problem for the world, doesn't matter if it's not a problem for any system, belief system you have, it's a problem for you because it's rooted in a wrong intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's rooted in restlessness, it's rooted in worry, it's rooted in hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you prioritize your ideas of how things should be and how the world should operate and how the mind should be in response?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you prioritize the actual live state of the king that's telling you... and you don't know why.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're just doing random stuff until, okay, he's pacified now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't have to deal with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to be at the mercy of the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to train it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way to train it, the only way to speak to it,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's through recognizing the level, the layer of the background where your intentions are, and then not making the wrong ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I always give that example, because it's like a kind of a good, simple textbook, conveys it well, which is like, even in the monasteries, like, you know, I don't know how many times I've seen that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everybody knows, you know, the suttas sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe not every monk is an expert or read them all, but they know sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they certainly know the suttas, you know, where the Buddha said, like, for example, you shouldn't say anything out of anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: If for you it's rooted in intentional ill-will, you shouldn't say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's the most beneficial thing for the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is your state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the monk wouldn't say until, basically, the anger has subsided, if the thing is not beneficial for both, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point was, everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, like, okay, you know, nobody will punch or physically attack anybody in the monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody will, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it might happen, but, say, most people wouldn't, you know, go really far in, like, an angry speech, would be able to restrain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, you know, mentally, like, hmm... it doesn't seem like a big deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I know it's a problem, but, yeah, you know, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, say, somebody does something annoying, junior monk does something annoying, and often you would see, like, a senior monk, you know, if he's maybe, like, really annoyed with it, he wouldn't do anything there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, say, next day, or two or three days later, same annoyance, by the way, the same choice, the same citta, pushing the same agenda on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, you know, three days now, three days it's been eating me.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I find an external justification to say something, or do I say there is no an external sign that can replace the internal recognition of the citta and the nimittas and the characteristics?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that's your value, you wouldn't do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if six months later, that same annoyance in regard to what somebody did, still there, you're still not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who knows?
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be for months.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depending on, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Depending on the mind of your mind, that you have no say in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it like this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't really matter, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, most of the monks that I remember, most of the people, basically, would find one reason or the other to justify and then say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would not say it through, like, anger or something, but it would always be... they would make a policy in the monastery or something or do a dhamma talk where it's just about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to preemptively address that, and basically, which becomes a form of acting out of that mind, because that uncertainty, abstaining from the wrong choice, it's increasing its weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can do it one day, two days, three days, maybe a week, but after a while,
[SPEAKER_00]: While it's increasing its weight, it's kind of decreasing its value.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it seems.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's also for the good of the monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what he did was factually wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Other people might do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then everything we worked for, this great dhamma, and the monastery we built, and inspiration we provide, everything will go to ruin.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your own crazy citta, untrained animal, trying to get you to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will tell you, hey, open the gate for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, no, I'm practicing restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you know, if you don't open the gates, things can happen out there, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Other, other, other animals can come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Issues can develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you sure you can live with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, yeah, I'm not opening the gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not opening the gate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you're not opening the gate, we're going to have a problem in here, plus the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, okay, okay, I'll open the gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's pretty much how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if people wouldn't open the gate, regardless of the irrationally... kind of... irrational... accumulation of the irrational, like increasingly more irrational scenarios that your mind is throwing at you, yet you still don't open the gate, you still don't make the right choice, you are on the track to be a sotāpanna, even if you don't want to become one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I said nobody can accidentally become a sotāpanna, because nobody will accidentally...
[SPEAKER_00]: Stick to this, which, as I said, it completely loses the value of... oh, but it's just... it's done for the good reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: While not doing it, it increases the weight that your mind threatens you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you just choose to... no, I'm still not going to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm still not going to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody will do that accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only persons that have understood sutta sufficiently
[SPEAKER_00]: Understood the importance of not acting out by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll stick to it, regardless of the storm that citta is cooking up, trying to scare you, so to open the gate, so it can go back to its wilderness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody is sotāpanna, it's because they made the right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody is not sotāpanna, it's because they haven't made the right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might have made all the effort in the world, in all the directions, but not the right one, not on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I kind of answered all the questions, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there's like one practical thing I received.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person asked, how should one practice while working or speaking or engaging with others?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, when a person has to attend to things, has to discuss stuff, has to plan and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, what do I do, in other words?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, everything we just described, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in other talks, well, you protect the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, say, say if your practice was before revolving around a bit kind of too much on the cushioned environment, you know, again, I remember, like, the places, monasteries around the world, where, like, even having to, like, you know, not by the place, but there were monks that even having to, like, sweep leaves or do stuff, any form of, like, like a physical exertion is just too disruptive for any mental equilibrium.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's kind of worse than a householder, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Householders don't have that privilege, don't have that luxury.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you can be protecting yourself all you want, the mind will be bombarded with stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you need to withdraw yourself to some extent, but the point is that it comes down to that, like, as I said,
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I might be afraid of doing it because I'm dependent on the cushion environment, but now I learned enough that those things shouldn't be a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do I engage with them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I keep an eye on the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: I keep an eye on my state of mind, my intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there might be states of fear and anxiety and uncertainty coming up because things are not in my control, you know, he can say this, she can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm accepting the outcomes of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody says something,
[SPEAKER_00]: That might make my cheetah just jump quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll focus on not acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter if that cheetah hurts then for next seven days.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll bear that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the outcome of the walking in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the pretty much how... how would it feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine, how would it feel to go with the grain?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would it feel to go against the grain?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would it feel to swim with the river?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would it feel to swim against the river?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddha said, dhamma goes against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You swim basically against the floods.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's gonna feel like... uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna feel like, oh, it's not right.
[SPEAKER_00]: If only I could resolve it mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: If only I could find justification.
[SPEAKER_00]: If only I could, you know, use psychoanalysis to find why this is so, so to give me a sense of, oh, now I know why it is, so it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It really doesn't matter whether it's because something happened in this life or previous or nothing really happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the mind of your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go worrying around why some random stranger has a preference of one kind as opposed to the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: You really wouldn't... you wouldn't worry about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do you worry about the preferences of your own citta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where they come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: You should only worry about whether you are giving in to them or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you have to engage with the world, when you have to engage with the things,
[SPEAKER_00]: Virtue, sense-restraint and the context on account of that, and then mental, as I said, mental choices, as much as obviously you are aware at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might be distracted and so on, and you might be mentally, like, accepting irritation or this or that, but at least you are recognizing that that is what's happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the broader context is keeping it all together, which is, well, I will not say anything or do anything by the body, regardless of what's happening to me, so to speak, how distracted I am, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you do fail, then recognize, okay, that was... that was too much, at least for now, so next time I should be even more careful before becoming that distracted, so that then I acted out by body or by speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, you can never be
[SPEAKER_00]: So distracted to become unaware of the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can be distracted so you don't see the choice when it comes up or when it starts coming up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only see when it's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: No amount of greed, aversion, delusion can make a choice for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If choices were to naturally and automatically follow, you know, what Abhidhamma and commentaries think, from greed, aversion, delusion and the states of mind of that, arahantri would never be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be a completely self-perpetuating thing and you couldn't come in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: But every single time, cetanā is always on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, indirectly, you are responsible for the states of your citta in that broadest sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not immediately, but in the broadest sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, kind of related to this question was another one that I received, which is
[SPEAKER_00]: So, say you are engaged with tasks, duties, work and so on, and things get a bit all unclear and muddy, and you lost your internal clarity and peace, things are disturbed, like, feels like a jungle.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you do there?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, do you stop, start counting your breath and stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, again, you might do those little things to help you cope, but you don't need to do any of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, what state of mind there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's a jungle, there's no clarity in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: This morning everything was so clear and calm and spacious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now it's just so cluttered.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all over the place.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your intention in regard to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Know that the mind is contained.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, not seeing that, you worry about, oh, it's like a jungle, the mind is cluttered, da-da.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, so you don't know the cluttered mind as cluttered mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to change the cluttered mind because it doesn't feel right because of your ideas or feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to change it into something else that suits your preferences better.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not the reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is the reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, King doesn't like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'll just keep serving it until he starts liking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I don't like when he doesn't like it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'll just force him into it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your mind is cluttered, gets busy, feels like a jungle, unreachable, not as peaceful, not as comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the state of mind that you know as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, oh, so what do I do in regard to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Without acting out, trying to change it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, again, that's how immediately you re-establish the context, by recognizing what your intention is in regard to any state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would it then be right to say that our intention is usually deeply rooted or connected with the feelings and our need to get rid or have more or distract ourselves from it, from the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah, like feeling, perception, intention, as the Sutta says, it's inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might start with, say, like more specific intentions, or I want to say this or do that, but ultimately, yes, you start going down the pathway of intentions, it's gonna come converge onto where things are felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're gonna start to recognize that simply because something is felt, agreeably,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even overly pleasant, you already have intention kind of towards it, to accept it and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those are subtle things, you know, they can become, say, they can be discerned in broad strokes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't really need to worry about, like, pinpoint on the level of feeling or something, because
[SPEAKER_00]: There are bigger impurities that are obstructing the citta way before that, which is other acts by body, speech and mind, habits that you're still tolerating while you know they're rooted in hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, deal with that first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the time will come when you recognize the subtle leanings of your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fatigue against the discomfort, leaning towards comfort, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, broadly, everything you do will fall into these three categories.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either for more pleasure, less pain, or ignorance of the... ignoring, distracting yourself from neither pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though the king is pleased with the right dishes, it seems that the mind is, at least initially, is pleased with the right choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would be the corresponding measure of rightness in the case of the citta?
[SPEAKER_00]: The corresponding... well, it would be basically the absence of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much why the four noble truths follow for the one that sees the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: which follows the one that's been training rightly in secluding himself from, internally, from greed, aversion, distraction and the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it becomes... that's the verification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not like, as I said, you're gonna have some grand reveal, like parting of the curtains and the truth shows itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna be like, you are unable to suffer, because the mind doesn't move in the way it used to move.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't latch, it doesn't bite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't, and you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it's like, oh, I live like a lotus in the filth, untouched by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I live in everything that used to cause issues and suffering, but untouched by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Sotāpanna already gets the taste of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he's certain, destined for awakening and has unshakable confidence in the fact that, well, knows that dhamma works.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if the whole world comes and tells you, no, the Buddha was actually wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by the way, the suttas were discovered.
[SPEAKER_00]: Turns out somebody wrote them 400 years ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, there's a proof.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they did the laser scanning and it was all discovered.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all hoax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that was a lucky hoax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by doing that, you're untouched by suffering internally, and nobody can, like... And it's not even a conviction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, because I convinced myself, I'll never think... No, it's literally, like, everything stays the same, yet animal cannot make you suffer anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you would know that the dhamma is actually right, even if, say, the historical Buddha never existed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, of course, it's impossible, because otherwise, like, you know, who could accidentally stumble upon the right instruction, unless somebody did it themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I'm just saying, hypothetically speaking, even if they prove that all the suttas are, like, written by somebody, it's like, well, that somebody freed himself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, on account of that somebody's instructions,
[SPEAKER_00]: I trained my own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I prepared the elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't flinch now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, the measure of it is there is no suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, obviously, you value that, but citta values that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's your duty to train it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same, same like with a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't know what it is actually good for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wants to go to the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wants to get into fights.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wants to go and mate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wants to do this, because it doesn't know
[SPEAKER_00]: That those things are actually not offering peace, are rooted in suffering and perpetuation of that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to show it otherwise and when it's eased, then it's liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you wouldn't have to do anything more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you say the hindrances are that tiny felt need to do something to be at ease?
[SPEAKER_00]: And we need to restrain and recognize that felt need as a burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Slavery.
[SPEAKER_00]: It finally helped to investigate this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: If my mind was truly free of hindrances, I would be at ease regardless of do X thing or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that I feel a need to do anything to be at ease, in and of itself is an obligation of slavery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I spoke about it in... well, in a number of old talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was referring to it as need to rest, like resting, which is exactly, I think, what you're referring to, the ease, which is, yeah, say, a presence of doubt,
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, the soul... the primary, the fundamental, the root reason for engaging with it, for being hindered by it, is because you're trying to get rid of the discomfort of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why a person who is gripped by the hindrance of doubt would be revolving around and getting to the right answer, but then having the need to repeat it again and again and again, because it was never really about the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about trying to find the ease which is measured by the absence of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is pretty much a common thread to all the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said in other talks, it's inherently felt as unpleasant, which is why you seek the desire, the objects of your desire and acting out to cover that up and hope to replace it with pleasure and ease from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I don't say it, I'm staying with a discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to be eased from it, so I'll... maybe I won't do anything physically, maybe I won't say anything, but mentally I'll justify it, I'll revolve around it, I'll make policies like the example I gave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that that's the only thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of... the hindrances are, as I said, they go as far
[SPEAKER_00]: As to have the intention just for that mindless ease from the uncomfortable feeling, at the expense of perspective, that's also hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But acting out physically, verbally, stuff, that is also hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sometimes people identify just with these coarse things and think, oh, I'm free from hindrances because I'm not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, are you free from the need for a gratuitous rest and ease?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because making the right choice is effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Needing to rest from doing it onto these things means giving way to the wild animal and allowing elephant to flinch and move and exercise some of its wild tendencies and preferences, because you can't be bothered.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, hindrances are pretty much, as I said, the scope of them
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes from one end all the way to the subtlest kind of willing choices and acceptances of forms of lust, aversion, distraction and unwholesome states like doubt, restlessness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you have anxiety or worry.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop the mind from arising like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the mind of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can certainly never give in to the tendency to, oh, let me... let me do this or that, or give in to it a bit, so it's not as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, let me open a gate a bit and let it go around and then it'll come back.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, let me allow its wilderness, because I can't be bothered to train it fully to the necessary extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you still remain under the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like with all the other aspects of training,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, things need to be addressed first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're worrying about the aspects of rest, not you specifically, but just generally a person, right, I mustn't rest internally, context protect, but then still tolerate choices of physical, acting out of physical lust and verbal and anger and so on, it's like, yeah, like you have a bigger fish to fry first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can see the scope and the subtlety and the depth of hindrances and address it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, could you say it's the unquestioned mission of this needs to be solved that is the problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is not the phenomenon of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much what we answered now.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is
[SPEAKER_00]: Like how the Sutta says, things like sign of beauty, sign of aversive, things suitable for doubt... Basically, the basis for hindrances are not what the hindrance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to deal with that means not basically failing to see that you're already hindered.
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you hindered?
[SPEAKER_00]: By wrongly attending to those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the
[SPEAKER_00]: The most basic definition of wrongly attending to something is thinking that that's a problem when it actually isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a form of ayoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking to some extent, this deserves giving in, so to get the ease and resolution and fixing and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that extent, it's ayoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the Buddha said, it's the ayoniso manasikāra that makes things that are basis for hindrances, to be the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the one who attends to them rightly, the sign of beauty remains, the sign of repulsive remains, things suitable for that... suitable to lend himself without, remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you're beyond hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I always go on about, you know, the whole kind of traditional common ideas, like, I must counter and deal with this or that, I must get rid of it, get rid of it, get rid of it, think the opposite, think the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yes, you're not seeing your mind there, you're just action-reaction, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, thoughts come up, I do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of just blindly, I do the opposite, because Buddhaghosa said so.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing the opposite?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, oh, because I absolutely hate the feeling of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, because you're acting out of your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how is that going to free you from hindrance?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why virtue, sensory strength, the gradual training before you can even come close to actually containing the hindrances rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when these thoughts present themselves, they will be pushing these choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yes, you don't welcome, entertain, choose, proliferate the thoughts of those choices, but you certainly don't try to, like, I must get rid of this state of citta altogether, because that would be rooted in pure aversion, pure resistance, which means that will hinder you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you address every hindrance through your methods and managements, it will continue to hinder you, because the roots of your intentions remain unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and acting along with that attitude of this is a problem, keeps giving it validity, keep making it a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeps making it a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's why, as I said just now, learning is important, so that you can shift the emphasis of your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you need to learn that that's not a problem, despite your whole being feeling, no, that is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: If only I say, do this, or react that, I will free myself from the confinement of this state of mind, of this problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have to go against that tendency, against that need.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only person who will do it, is the one that heard many times that, actually, no, that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trust me on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Try doing it and you'll see it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, literally, like a doctor telling you, stop eating that, it's harming you, but you don't see the connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't trust the doctor and you continue eating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, for whatever, like, some person might actually, for one reason or the other, choose to, okay, I'll trust the doctor and, despite not having any problem with his food, not any issue with his food, I will stop eating it, because he said so, and maybe other symptoms will then show and I can see for myself that actually, yes, he was a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a degree of faith is necessary, even when it comes to this.